Israel has begun what prime minister
Benjamin Netanyahu calls the second
stage of the war by expanding its
military ground operations in Gaza we
spoke with vice president kamla Harris
this past week as the Biden
Administration was trying to balance
Israel's need to retaliate against Hamas
with the urgent need to get relief to
the Palestinian people vice president
Harris told us she is also involved in
the administration's efforts on the war
in Ukraine as well as countless
intractable problems including gun
violence at home but with the Middle
East on a Razor's Edge we started our
conversation
there the story will continue in a
moment how close is this to becoming a
regional conflict that could draw in US
troops we have absolutely no intention
nor do we have any plans to send
combat troops into Israel or Gaza period
vice president Harris told us the US is
not telling Israel what to do but is
providing advice equipment and
diplomatic support a terrorist
organization Hamas
slaughtered hundreds of young people at
a concert by most estimates at least,
1400 Israelis are dead Israel without
any question has a right to defend
itself that being said it is very
important that there be no conflation
between Hamas and the Palestinians the
Palestinians
deserve equal measures of Safety and
Security self-determination and dignity
and we have been very clear that the
rules of war must be adhered to and that
there be human humanitarian Aid that
flows she told told us the US wants to
keep the conflict from escalating but
that's proving difficult in the last two
weeks Hezbollah in lebanan and the
houthis in Yemen both proxies of Iran
have launched missiles rockets and
drones against Israel and Iranian backed
militias have fired on US troops
stationed in Iraq and Syria in response
the US launched air strikes against
Iranian weapons facilities in Syria if
that weren't enough of a signal to Iran
and other adversaries the Pentagon has
also deployed two imposing aircraft
carrier strike groups to the region and
what's the message to Iran
don't as President Biden said just don't
exactly one word pretty
straightforward since the Hamas attack
on Israel the Vice President says she
has spoken with President Isaac Herzog
of Israel and joined President Biden on
calls with prime minister Benjamin
Netanyahu and Palestinian Authority
president Mahmud abas President Joe
Biden told us in a statement this is as
high stakes and complex a situation as
it gets and kamla is my partner in all
of it he told us Harris's advice and
counsel are
invaluable when he was vice president Mr
Biden famously said that he wanted to be
the last person in the room with
President Obama do you have that
relationship with President Biden I do
you do I do and um and I take that
responsibility quite seriously how often
do you meet with him multiple times a
day quite often unless he or I are
traveling they're in total agreement the
US must stand with Israel and Ukraine
two democracies under attack we
are as
committed to Ukraine as we've always
been to
authorize additional Aid to defend
itself against Russia's unprovoked
aggression that is not going to waver
does this war in the Middle East put
Ukraine on a back burner not for us no
it does not put us put them on a back
burner at
all vice president Harris has visited 19
countries and met with more than 100
world
leaders but lately she has been the
administration's Point person on
domestic priorities traveling the
country talking up the Democrats key
issues before the 2024 election issues
she hopes will fire up the base but are
bound to inflame the
GOP she went to North Carolina to Mark
the anniversary of the Supreme Court
overturning Ro v Wade how dare they
attack our fundamental
rights how dare they attack our freedom
in Virginia it was Guns our nation is
being torn apart by gun
violence we joined the vice president
and second gentleman Doug mhof on Air
Force 2 for a trip to Las Vegas it was 5
days after the terror attack on Israel
welcome on Bo thank
you while in the air the vice president
joined a secure video call with the
president and their national security
teams to discuss measures to keep the
Homeland safe
once on the ground in Las
Vegas vice president Harris went to the
College of Southern Nevada the eighth
stop on her fight for our freedoms
College Tour because you voted Joe Biden
is president of the United States and I
am Vice President of the United States
because you voted but nationally the
Biden Harris Administration is not
generating the kind of enthusiasm she's
seeing on her tour a recent CBS poll
found that at the beginning of President
Biden's term 70% of young people people
under 30 said he was doing a good job
now it's less than
50% why is that what's going on if you
pull how young people feel about the
climate and the warming of our planet it
pulls as one of their top concerns when
we talk about what we are doing with
student loan debt polls very high the
challenge that we have as an
Administration is we got to let people
know who BR it to them that's our
challenge but it is not that the work we
are doing is not very very popular with
a lot of people she blames the
disconnect in part on lack of media
coverage still the vice president
herself is not very popular now just 41%
of adults told CBS news they approve of
the job she's doing about the same for
President Biden we talked to her the day
before the Carnage in Maine but she had
told us issues like mass shootings are
more important than poll numbers you
have a portfolio that includes gun
violence the root cause of migration
these are some of the most intractable
issues facing the country we've done
some of the most significant gun safety
laws in 30 years but we still need an
assault weapons ban it doesn't have to
be this way there was an assault weapons
ban at one time it expired let's renew
it most Americans say that they don't
think you're doing a good job on the
border you and the administration the
number of people trying to cross the US
Southern border is at an all-time high
it's no secret that we have a broken
immigration system shortterm we need a
safe orderly and Humane border policy
and long-term we need to invest in the
root causes of migration but the bottom
line Congress needs to act come on
participate in the solution instead of
political gamesmanship if politics is a
game kamla Harris has proven herself to
be a Savvy player forging a career that
has gone from one first to another the
child of an Indian mother and a Jamaican
father she was the first woman district
attorney for San Francisco the first
woman to serve as California attorney
general the first woman of color elected
senator from California so help me God
and the first woman and woman of color
to be elected vice president of the
United States being in that unique
position being that first yeah does that
bring added pressure no doubt no doubt
you know my mother she would say KLA you
may be the first to do many things make
sure you're not the
last and among the
responsibilities that I carry and maybe
impose on myself that is one of them so
this was she showed us around the vice
president's ceremonial office I brought
in this bust of th Good Marshall uh and
I always have him over my right shoulder
in the drawer here the desk where
previous vice presidents left their
signatures alore Quail Cheney Harry
Truman some of these men went on to
become president but kamla Harris told
us she is focused on getting the Biden
Harris ticket reelected next year the
GOP is using her low poll numbers and
President Biden's age as a battering ram
and some Democrats are growing worried
we were talking to some democratic
donors and they have told us that should
something befall President Biden and he
is not able to run that there would be a
freefor all for who would run as
president you are in the spot that that
would be a natural for you to step up
but we're hearing from donors that they
would not naturally fall into line why
is that well first of all I'm not going
to engage in that hypothetical because
Joe Biden is very much alive and running
for re-election so you do know I mean
that is a concern and and a legitimate
concern I would say I hear from a lot of
different people a lot of different
things but let me just tell you I'm
focused on the job I truly am our
democracy is on the line bill and I
frankly in my head do not have time for
parlor games when we have a president
who is running for
reelection that's it Joe Biden
conventional wisdom is that most
presidential elections are won or lost
on the economy and while inflation has
been coming down prices for Basics like
food and shelter remain staggeringly
high we came into office during the
height of a pandemic record
unemployment and because of our economic
policies we now are reducing inflation
we have created over 14 million new jobs
we've created over 800,000 new
manufacturing jobs wages are up and so
we've seen great progress considering
what you are laying out as your
achievements you have the current front
runner for the GOP Donald Trump facing
what 91 criminal charges I've lost count
yet the Biden Harris ticket is running
neck and neck with Donald Trump why are
you not 30 points ahead well I'm not I'm
not a political pundit so I I I'm not
going to speak to that but what I will
say is this when the American people are
able to take a close look at election
time on their options I think the choice
is going to be clear Bill we're going to
win let me just tell you that we're
going to
win and I'm not saying it's going to be
easy but we will win you say that with
such conviction I have no doubt but I
also have no doubt it's going to be a
lot of work and everyone's going to have
to participate this is a
democracy democracy she said that word
often during our interview despite the
criticism and low poll numbers former
prosecutor kamla Harris told us she's
prepared to trust the verdict of the
American people do you have to ask
yourself why are people seeming not to
hear our message I look at it more as
let's keep getting out there and as with
any election we got to make our case to
the American people that's part of our
responsibility and that's this process
and that's what it is and that's a fair
process