2023 has been a year of soldout Stadium
concerts but only one of the women
breaking attendance records has built a
global brand singing upside down
highflying stunts are only part of her
appeal Alicia Moore is known as much for
her party anthems as her Powerhouse
voice and if the name is unfamiliar it's
because she's best known by her one-word
professional identity pink pink famously
has no filter and fans who have followed
her 25y year career have come to expect
her to share every detail of her
sometimes troubled
story the story will continue in a
moment do I have this right you're
willing to talk about anything any
question is fine there's no offense
taken yeah it's all I'm I'm open to all
of it a lot of people in your world
thrive on protecting privacy
you're an open book why I guess I look
at it in a very specific way if I'm a
mystery to you how can I expect you to
connect with me and if I'm a person
that's desperate for connection then why
would mystery be interesting to me I
want to know you I want you to know me
all right you guys want to start with
start by coming to one of her concerts
we were there for her homecoming shows
in Philadelphia last month One Stop on a
year and a half long tour hello
beautiful people
she's already set attendance records in
stadiums around the
world and sold more than $350 million in
[Music]
[Applause]
tickets a pink concert is part Rock
rager Park Broadway spectacle never
going
to again never going
to
again with some Tinker Bells sprinkled
[Applause]
in she belts out her hits while flipping
and flying 100 fet in the air and she
does it without lip
syncing when she says she actually sings
better upside down
believer
Now 44 when she looks out into the crowd
she sees a lot more moms and dads she
calls herself and her fans the uncool
kids and takes great pleasure in taking
on their haters whether in her shows or
on social media her message is don't
mess with them or
me this image that you've created you've
got this famous
snarl yeah right I wonder if when that
started the message was this is a woman
that you don't want to mess with well
this is a woman you don't want to mess
with is a true statement I know what
certain people think of when they look
at me down to the fact that I'm muscular
I'm outspoken and I have short hair I'm
possibly a dude definitely a lesbian
people sort of put you in a box no
matter what you look like and my box
happens to be if if you're outspoken and
you don't sort of Bend to societal Norms
then you're scary and dangerous and the
reality is the reality is I am the
goofiest most fun loving person that
will possibly kick your ass if I have
to come on children these days life is
less get the party started and more get
these kids to bed her six-year-old son
Jameson push and 12-year-old daughter
Willow are often on tour with her riding
their scooters on stage during sound
checks for the hometown show in Philly
Pink's husband Motocross star Carrie
Hart was there and so was her mom Judy
this is our tour Library backstage
there's a library where the team swaps
books pink has a romantic novel she
needs to return we have a
little sheet you actually have a sign
wish I had the thing but we don't have
that so I've been backstage for other
artists and some of the things I've seen
are lot of booze lot of party cool my
dressing room used to be like whiskey
and cigarettes then it was ball pits and
stuffed
animals when she's not on the road she's
home in Southern
California this is where she's Alicia
Moore a mohawk wearing mom who bakes
sourdough and is part of the
PTA she's either driving for school drop
off or or driving a forklift on her 25
acre Vineyard she says she schooled
herself on the science of wine making by
studying lat to the night after her
shows so do I have this correct you
don't make pink Rosé I do not make pink
Rosé my ganache is it looks like a white
wine occasionally it's a bit Peach but
you drink it I drink a lot well Biggie
Smalls once said never get high on your
own Supply but he sure did I do make a
lot of wine home is also where she makes
music this is my music room it's really
great yeah she's a writer on most of her
songs and says no topic is off limits
not even the ups and downs in her
marriage and you taught yourself to play
on this sort of kind of I mean I can
play halves of songs one of my favorite
songs is Make You Feel My Love and I
played this every day during
Co this is a bob Dylan song made most
recently Famous by Adele it's one of my
favorite
songs when the rain is blowing in your
face and the whole world is on your
c i could offer you a warm
embrace To Make You Feel My
Love so I played that every day wow
until I was good enough to go on stage
and play an instrument she grew up
singing opera and gospel in Doylestown
Pennsylvania but she says tension at
home made her desperate to leave she
calls her relationship with her father
Jim Moore complicated he served in
Vietnam and passed away two years ago as
a teen arguments with her mother were so
bad pink says one fight got physical and
her mom fell down stairs she now calls
that her one regret in life you said you
were the kid that other moms didn't want
their kids to play with why I was a punk
I had a mouth I was I had a chip on my
shoulder basically I grew up in a house
where every day my parents were
screaming at each other throwing things
hated each other and then I got into
drugs I was selling drugs and then I was
kicked out of the house I dropped out of
high school I was off the rails what
happened on Thanksgiving in
1995 Thanksgiving of 1995 I was at a
rave
and I
overdosed I was
on oh boy
ecstasy angel dust Crystal all kinds of
things and then I was out done too much
you almost died yeah remember she says
that was the end of hard drugs for her
and weeks later got her first record
deal as the lead singer in an R&B girl
group but they didn't last long so when
you're starting out the industry sort of
seems like they've got you going down a
path they paint you with an R&B brush
yes I signed to laf face records we were
the token white girls on a black label I
was told to take etiquette classes very
early on uh they wanted me to learn how
to wear dresses and use the Right Fork
how'd that work out I went once but it
didn't work what did they not like I
think they were trying to turn me into
something that I didn't want to be image
is everything in this business using her
teenage nickname pink she went solo and
her first album was an R&B double
Platinum
success she then broadened her sound to
include Rock and
pop and not so subtly named her next
album
misunderstood it was a career defining
hit selling 15 million cop cies around
the
[Music]
[Applause]
world you'd said in the past it felt
like you were never winning the
popularity contest among your peers what
do you mean by that we sold 3 million
tickets in the last 6 months but you
don't really hear about it unless you
went so at the end of the day do I give
a who talks about me as long as the mom
and the daughter or the dad who's in the
pink T-shirt as well as his daughter and
her three friends had a fantastic time
or the gay couple that came together and
felt super safe at my show because no
one heckled
them that's what really
matters and then there's
this
we wanted to know how she does it
singing upside down as an asmatic no
less well it took a lot of childhood
gymnastics classes and tortured training
sessions with her aerialist coach Drea
Weber okay tighten up your stomach ready
be nice now sing where there is there is
beame come on there is a flame someone B
to get burned just because it burns
doesn't mean you're going to die you got
to
get I'm not just a singer I'm a gymnast
I can do all kinds of things I'm
physical this body like this the muscles
that that scare people are it's my power
right it's like I don't eat well to look
good I eat well to go far fast and
hard at 53 she is all muscle and make no
mistake as tough as she looks
[Applause]
I realized that the machete that I've
always carried this metaphorical machete
that I've always carried that made me a
really difficult kid is what makes me
really good at what I did today and it
makes me a Survivor do you feel like you
needed that hard Edge that machete to
climb as far as you've climbed in this
business absolutely I never got a record
deal because I was cute I got a record
deal cuz I was fiery I had a lot to say
and I had a voice so I'm relieved I
don't have to fall back on sort of
conventional Beauty and and that doesn't
have to be my thing and I don't have to
keep that up either as I age I don't
have to be that I can be all of this she
won't need a plan B anytime soon but as
she told us at midnight over a glass of
wine in her dressing room in
Philadelphia she is planning the next
chapter it's what any self-respecting
acrobatic sequin loving Entertainer
would do a Las Vegas
[Music]
residency I would like to have the best
show that Vegas has ever seen and I
think that I can for a performer like me
to have a stage that doesn't have to
travel oh my God you can do so much so
all these years in what's the hardest
part about your job now I guess that I
keep demanding more and more and more
and more from myself physically
emotionally
spiritually vocally I want to raise the
bar all the time and I'm sort of going
against time right how do you keep out
doing that I like going against societal
Norms when they say a woman has to slow
down become smaller take up less space
calm down no absolutely not why who says
why can't we ride till the wheels fall
off that's what I plan on
doing go backstage with pink after a
concert come on get in at 60 minutes
overtime.com