Rich Paul has become one of the Premier
agents in professional sports he counts
LeBron James as a close friend and
client the agency he founded clutch
Sports Group made deals worth almost
$900 million this past summer for his
NBA clients alone Paul honed his deal
making instincts as a kid navigating
what he called the Hostile streets of
his Cleveland neighborhood today at 42
he's rewriting the playbook for
representing pro athletes Rich Paul told
us he was lucky and when you hear his
story we think you'll understand
why the story will continue in a
moment so did you used to come to games
when you were younger I went one time
when I had to um sit all the way up at
the top you really couldn't couldn't see
the person and
now now it's now you're sitting on the
floor we joined Rich Paul courtside at a
Cleveland Cavaliers game last season he
seemed to know
everyone what up do what's good and it
seemed everyone wanted to know
him thank you so much you're my ID bro
thank you brother I appreciate it last
year Paul got Cleveland star Darius
Garland a $200 million deal the richest
in franchise history Garland is one of
nearly 200 athletes on Paul's roster who
are some of the big names that we would
all recognize which sport you want I
mean we just had Jaylen herzon and
Devonte Smith playing the Super Bowl for
the Philadelphia Eagles and then you got
the Anthony Davis's and uh Draymond
greens and obviously LeBron do you know
the total value of the contracts you've
negotiated I would say it's close to 3
billion I think it's more than 4 billion
but it's hard to keep track when you're
always on the go showtime baby before
the NBA draft in New York City we
watched him work the phones you know
it's draft day man anything can happen
work the room hey coach how you doing
man right and work the angles to move
clients like Duke Center Derek Lively II
up the draft board you ready sir in
college Lively was known for his defense
but Paul had him work on his three-point
shot and before the draft invited teams
to see Lively shot up to the 12th pick
about 10 spots higher than first
projected it might not look like it but
Rich Paul is a towering figure in the
NBA I've always been the smallest guy in
the
room willing to take the biggest swing
some of his biggest swings have been for
his biggest client LeBron James Paul
negotiated his jumps from Miami to
Cleveland to LA a deals that netted
James $400 million and set him up to win
two of his four
championships he told us he works to
give players leverage some people say
that you're destroying the player
loyalty to the teams and the fans player
loyalty to what if I can be traded in
the middle of the night to another team
what I should be is educating myself to
where if this isn't going the way I
thought it was supposed to go I can
switch up right we're not I have options
I have op what's the sister to having
money with no
options that's apparently how Superstar
Anthony Davis felt in 2018 the New
Orleans Center had a $127 million
contract but was tired of losing so he
fired his agent and hired Rich Paul Paul
flouted NBA rules by publicly demanding
a trade earning the wrath of fans and a
$50,000 fine for Davis the drama landed
Paul on the cover of Sports Illustrated
which called him the most polarizing
figure in the
NBA when it was someone that didn't look
like me it was genius it was why you get
a power agent but when it's me I'm
destroying the league I mean those
things are absurd he got d us what he
wanted a championship ring and a deal
now worth $270
million there's a saying that goes if
you a got no haters you ain't
popping so you must be popping I think
I'm popping a little bit you know he was
popping a lot at his annual allstar game
party this past winter in Salt Lake City
is that we dropped in and saw giants of
the court mingling with rappers team
owners and Titans of Industry over
cocktails and canipes Rich Paul had a
full plate of business options one from
the president of Gatorade I want to be a
first call done while we were chatting
with
him Golden State Warrior Draymond Green
cut in the four-time NBA champion cycled
through two other agents before signing
up with Rich Paul who landed him a $100
million contract over the summer so then
you end up a young black man who's made
more money than you can ever imagine but
you don't know how to live with it you
don't know what to do with it and what
does he do most agents treat athletes as
if the athlete work for them but there's
a multi-billion Dollar
business going on around most athletes
that they don't understand but they
don't have a rich part to teach them and
that's what's special about it Paul's
improbable Journey the subject of his
new Memoir out this week started on the
east side of Cleveland in the early
1980s just as crack cocaine hit the
streets when he was about 4 he learned
his mother manura was hooked on crack
his father Big Rich recognized his son's
intelligence and kept him close though
they lived apart he owned the
neighborhood convenience store so your
dad's store was just right in here yeah
and this was this was my world this now
empty Corner was a hot bed of activity
legal and illegal it was a shootout
right here on this corner Big Rich
taught his son to always think two steps
ahead he scraped together the money to
send him to a Catholic High School away
from the neighborhood still there was no
avoiding the streets you don't know what
you're in that's your Norm that's my
Norm sardines out the can that was
today's version of tuna tartar on the
Waldorf
rooftop know this was my education
though this was this was my Harvard my
Michigan my morehous and the same things
I learned on this corner I take it to
the board room because the one thing
this teaches you that I don't think you
can learn from those institutions is
people
characters and on these streets it's no
better way to learn character because
they're coming with everything his dad
taught him another skill a way to make
money if all else fails with a Pair of
Dice Paul and his best friend Edward
given were regulars at an open air
Casino in the park 50 people crowded
around this little area and the energy
was high it was it was an arena and Rich
Paul was a natural and how much would
you earn I mean a slow day was $1,000
and a not slow day
H you know four or five $4 or 5,000 easy
when you were 14 15 16 oh yeah what did
you learn from this experience you gain
a resilience here we won majority of the
time but you also had to learn how to
lose he suffered his biggest loss when
he was 19 his father died from cancer
and Paul went all in on the streets
selling marijuana and crack cocaine this
is the very drug that your mother was
hooked on the absence of my
dad allowed me to to take that step
because I would have never done that had
he
been around I had too much respect for
him if it's not something that I would
sit here and and glorify it almost
sounds like you were a full-time Hustler
oh yeah but Jeff Bezos is a
hustler think he's not Phil Knight was
the ultimate Hustler the difference is
they could go with their plan and their
business
idea and get someone to believe in them
it didn't matter what idea I had there's
no Pathway to get there he found one
through a stroke of luck at the akan
Canton Airport in 2001 Paul was wearing
a throwback jersey like this one that
caught the eye of another traveler High
School hoop sensation LeBron James what
did you see in him it began with him you
know wearing a throwback jersey that I
you know loved but as we got to talk
about sports we started evolving and
even talking more and more just about
life and about our upbringing about our
our moms and and and our communities and
stuff of that nature and it um just kind
of struck it just struck a core when
James entered the NBA he hired Rich Paul
as a right-hand man Paul went on to work
for LeBron's agent and watched listened
and learned
I understand that you would go into
meetings with the likes of Warren
Buffett being in those
rooms is much better
to to listen than to talk if you listen
you might actually learn something and
you start to kind of you know work your
way on your own after just four years he
struck out on his own and launched
clutch Sports Group in 2012 LeBron James
went with him when you first started
this you were underestimated Not only
was I underestimated I was also not
wanted I didn't look like the success in
our industry especially from a place of
decision-making and I wanted to disrupt
the industry I wanted to be impactful
but I wanted to come from a place of
purpose in 2013 with his first
negotiation as agent for Phoenix Sons
guard Eric bledo he proved the naysayers
wrong he said the sons had offered $28
million and then $48 million and you
turned it down yeah but what was on the
line my
career everyone was calling and saying
he's crazy he don't know what he's doing
he's an experienced it sounds like you
are really comfortable rolling the dice
I was born a dice roller his gamble paid
off after hanging tough for a year
clutch got bled so a $70 million deal 42
million more than the son's first offer
great room today clutch has 70 employees
with offices in Los Angeles New York and
Atlanta and they both in the same draft
class Paul teamed up with Powerhouse
agency UTA to expand clutch's reach I
had to build a multi 100 million dollar
company to get people to believe in me
and there's still doubt critics say he's
only successful because of his
relationship with you I mean it's
disappointing to hear that would you
gave him an opportunity yeah and I don't
give people opportunities much um and he
took well Way Beyond um than what he
even imagined Rich Paul now has a new
balance signature shoe a first for an
agent his partner is more famous than he
is he's been in a relationship with
Adele for 2 and A2 years Adele she gave
him a shout out at the Grammys oh God
Rich he he said don't cry if you win
anything tonight don't cry and here I am
crying a couple of weeks later at his
allstar game party Paul's friends
recognized his achievements from us this
from us with a
$140,000 watch
wow
wow wow do you have to pinch yourself
sometimes all the time I had it worse
than a lot of people but I evolved I
matured I transitioned how's that feel
feels great it feels
earned you know it wasn't given for sure
it was earned which is good I like
that