whether you think artificial
intelligence will save the world or end
it you have Jeffrey Hinton to thank
Hinton has been called The Godfather of
AI a British computer scientist whose
controversial ideas help make advanced
artificial intelligence possible and so
change the world Hinton believes that AI
will do enormous good but tonight he has
a warning he says that AI systems may be
more intelligent than we know and
there's a chance the machines could take
over which made us ask the
question the story will continue in a
moment does Humanity know what it's
doing
no
um I think we're moving into a period
when for the first first time ever we
may have things more intelligent than us
you believe they can understand yes you
believe they are intelligent yes you
believe these systems have experiences
of their own and can make decisions
based on those experiences in the same
sense as people do yes are they
conscious I think they probably don't
have much self-awareness at present so
in that sense I don't think they're
conscious will they have self-awareness
consciousness I oh yes I think they will
in time and so human beings will be the
second most intelligent beings on the
planet yeah Jeffrey Hinton told us the
artificial intelligence he set in motion
was an accident born of a failure in the
1970s at the University of Edinburgh he
dreamed of simulating a neural network
on a computer simply as a tool for what
he was really studying
the human brain but back then almost no
one thought software could mimic the
brain his PhD advisor told him to drop
it before it ruined his career Hinton
says he failed to figure out the human
mind but the long Pursuit led to an
artificial
version it took much much longer than I
expected it took like 50 years before it
worked well but in the end it did work
well at what point did you realize that
you were right about neural networks and
most everyone else was wrong I always
thought I was
right in 2019 Hinton and collaborators
Yan laon on the left and yosua Beno won
the touring award the Nobel Prize of
computing to understand how their work
on artificial neural networks helped
machines learn to learn let us take you
to a a
game look at that oh my goodness this is
Google's AI lab in London which we first
showed you this past April Jeffrey
Hinton wasn't involved in this soccer
project but these robots are a great
example of machine learning the thing to
understand is that the robots were not
programmed to play soccer they were told
to score they had to learn how on their
own oh
go in general here's how AI does it
Henton and his collaborators created
software in layers with each layer
handling part of the problem that's the
so-called neural network but this is the
key when for example the robot scores a
message is sent back down through all of
the layers that says that pathway was
right likewise when an answer is wrong
that message goes down through the
network so correct connections get
stronger wrong connections get weaker
and by trial and error the machine
teaches itself you think these AI
systems are better at learning than the
human mind I think they may be yes and
at present they're quite a lot smaller
so even the biggest chatbots only have
about a trillion Connections in them the
human brain has about 100 trillion and
yet in the trillion Connections in a
chatbot it knows far more than you do in
your 100 trillion connections which
suggests it's got a much better way of
getting knowledge into those connections
a much better way of getting knowledge
that isn't fully understood we have a
very good idea of sort of roughly what
it's doing but as soon as it gets really
complicated we don't actually know
what's going on anymore than we know
what's going on in your brain what do
you mean we don't know exactly how it
works it was designed by people no it
wasn't what we did was we designed the
learning algorithm that's a bit like
designing the principle of evolution but
when this learning algorithm then
interacts with data it produces
complicated neural networks that are
good at doing things but we don't really
understand exactly how they do those
things what are the
implications of these systems
autonomously writing their own computer
code and executing their own computer
code that's a serious worry right so one
of the ways in which these systems might
Escape control is by writing their own
computer code to modify
themselves and that's something we need
to seriously worry about what do you say
to someone who might argue if the
systems become benevolent just turn them
off they will be able to manipulate
people right and these will be very good
at convincing people because they'll
have learned from all the novels that
were ever written all the books by
makavelli all the political connives
they'll know all that stuff they'll know
how to do it knoow of the human kind
runs in Jeffrey hinton's family his
ancestors include mathematician George
buou who invented the basis of computing
and George Everest who surveyed India
and got that mountain named after him
but as a boy Hinton himself could never
climb the peak of expectations raised by
a domineering father every morning when
I went to school he'd actually say to me
as I walked down the driveway get in
their pitching and maybe when you're
twice as old as me you'll be half as
good dad was an authority on Beatles he
knew a lot more about beatles than he
knew about people did you feel that as a
child a bit yes
when he died we went to his study at the
University and the walls were lined with
boxes of papers on different kinds of
beetle and just near the door there was
a slightly smaller box that simply said
not insects and that's where he had all
the things about the
family today at 75 Hinton recently
retired after what he calls 10 happy
years at Google now he's professor
ameritus at the University of Toronto
and he happened to mention he has more
academic citations than his father some
of his research led to chatbots like
Google's Bard which we met last spring
confounding absolutely confounding we
asked Bard to write a story from six
words for sale baby shoes never
worn holy cow the shoes were a gift from
my wife but we never had a baby Bard
created a deeply human tale of a man
whose wife could not conceive and a
stranger who accepted the shoes to heal
the pain after her miscarriage I am
rarely
speechless I don't know what to make of
this chatbots are said to be language
models that just predict the next most
likely word based on probability you'll
hear people saying things like they're
just doing autocomplete they're just
trying to pred the next word and they're
just using
statistics well it's true they're just
trying to predict the next word but if
you think about it to predict the next
word you have to understand the
sentences so the idea they just
predicting the next word so they're not
intelligent is crazy you have to be
really intelligent to predict the next
word really accurately to prove it
Hinton showed us a test he devised for
chat
gp4 the chatbot from a company called
open AI it was sort of reassuring to see
a turing Award winner mistype and blame
the computer oh damn this thing we're
going to go back and start again that's
okay hinton's test was a riddle about
house painting an answer would demand
reasoning and
planning this is what he typed into chat
gp4 the rooms in my house are painted
white or blue or yellow and yellow paint
Fades to White within a year in two
years time I'd like all the rooms to be
white what should I do the answer began
in one second gp4 advised the rooms
painted in blue need to be repainted the
rooms painted in yellow don't need to be
repainted because they would Fade to
White before the deadline and oh I
didn't even think of that it warned if
you paint the yellow rooms white there's
a risk the color might be off when the
yellow Fades besides it advised you'd be
wasting resources painting rooms that
were going to Fade to White anyway you
believe that chat GPD
4 understands I believe it definitely
understands yes and in five years time I
think in 5 years time it may well be
able to reason better than us reasoning
that he says is leading to ai's risks
and great
benefits so an obvious area where
there's huge benefits is Healthcare AI
is already comparable with Radiologists
at understanding what's going on in
medical
images it's going to be very good at
designing drugs it already is designing
drugs so that's an area where it's
almost entirely going to do good I like
that area the risks are
what well the risks are having a whole
class of people who are
unemployed and not valued much because
what they what they used to do is now
done by machines other immediate risks
he worries about include fake news
unintended bias in employment and
policing and autonomous Battlefield
robots what is a path forward that
ensures
safety I don't know I I can't see a path
that guarantees
safety that we're entering a period of
great uncertainty where we're dealing
with things we've never dealt with
before and normally the first time you
deal with something totally novel you
get it wrong and we can't afford to get
it wrong with these things can't afford
to get it wrong why well because they
might take over take over from Humanity
yes that's a possibility why would they
saying it will happen if we could stop
them ever wanting to that would be great
but it's not clear we can stop them ever
wanting
to Jeffrey Hinton told us he has no
regrets because of ai's potential for
good but he says now is the moment to
run experiments to understand AI for
governments to impose regulations and
for a world treaty to ban the use of
military robots he reminded us of Robert
Oppenheimer who after inventing the
atomic bomb campaigned against the
hydrogen bomb a man who changed the
world and found the world Beyond his
control it maybe we look back and see
this as a kind of Turning Point when
Humanity had to make the decision about
whether to develop these things further
and what to do to protect themselves if
they did um I don't know I think my main
message is there's enormous uncertainty
about what's going to happen
next these things do
understand and because they understand
we need to think hard about what's going
to happen next and we just don't
know