General Mark Millie completed a
four-year term as chairman of the Joint
Chiefs of Staff the nation's highest
ranking military officer on September
30th he told us he spent most of his
time working to avoid a direct conflict
with Russia and China while the country
watched him have a very public falling
out with former president Trump the man
who picked him for the job General
Millie's times serving President Joe
Biden had its own challenges including
America's calamitous withdrawal from
Afghanistan as well as providing Ukraine
with billions of dollars worth of
American military equipment a few hours
before we sat down with the general at
the Pentagon he'd had his final phone
call with the commander of Ukraine's
armed
forces the story will continue in a
moment the counter offensive that the
ukrainians are running is still ongoing
um the progress as uh many many people
have noted is slow but it is steady and
they are making progress on a day-to-day
basis but expelling 200,000 Russian
soldiers No Easy Task very hard very
hard how long is this going to look like
this a year five years well you can't
put a Time on it but it'll be a
considerable length of time and it's
going to be long and hard and very
bloody Russia occupies 41,000 square
miles of Ukraine the front line extends
about the distance from Atlanta to
Washington DC in Congress this past week
Republicans ended Kevin McCarthy's
speakership and for now more Aid to
Ukraine according to the White House of
the 113 billion already committed
there's only enough left to last a few
more months with all of the issues
facing Americans at home why is this
worth it if Ukraine loses and Putin wins
I think you would be certainly
increasing if not doubling your defense
budget in the years ahead and you will
increase the probability of a great
power war in the next 10 to 15 years I
think it' be a very dangerous situation
if if Putin's allowed to win Ukraine
Russia obviously is what drives this
meeting today the chairman of the Joint
Chiefs is the commander and Chief's
principal military adviser but commands
no troops in battle I am obligated uh
regardless of consequences to give my
advice to the president but no president
is obligated to follow that advice this
past August General Millie invited us to
board the USS Constitution in Boston
Harbor not far from where he grew up
we're the only uh military in the world
that swear an oath not to a king a queen
a tyrant a wouldbe tyrant or a dictator
we swear an oath to an idea the idea
that is American it's and it's embodied
in that document the Constitution which
sets up our form of government in 2021
General Millie had counseled President
Biden to keep 2,500 troops in and around
Cobell instead Mr Biden ordered a
complete withdrawal to end America's
longest war after 20 years the disaster
that followed will be part of both of
their legacies I go through the entire
uh withdrawal from uh Afghanistan
chapter and verse all the time that was
a a strategic failure for the United
States the enemy occupied the capital
city of the country that you were
supporting so to me uh that hurts it
hurts a big way but no matter what pain
I feel or anyone else feels nothing
comes even close to the pain of those
that were killed to those who served in
Afghanistan for two decades and lost
family members and friends and wonder
was it worth it that's always the
question right so 2461 killed in action
by the enemy in Afghanistan over 20
years was it worth it look at I can't
answer that for other people this is a
tough business that we're in this
military business it's unforgiving The
Crucible of combat's unforgiving people
die they lose their arms they lose their
legs it's an incredibly difficult uh
life but is it worth it look around you
uh look ask yourself the question uh for
me I've answered it many many times over
and that's why I stay in uniform and
that's why I maintain my oath his
commitment to that oath would be both
tested and questioned by Donald Trump
while their relationship began with kind
words uh Mark Milly he's a great
gentleman he's a great Patriot he's a
great Soldier after the January 6th
Insurrection the two men would not speak
again what do we want we their public
estrangement started in the spring of
2020 when protests for racial Justice
some violent spread across the country
including to Washington DC perhaps more
than any other chairman in the role you
have become ins snarled in politics and
arguably threats to the Constitution
what have you learned from that well I
think it's important to to keep your
North Star which is the Constitution we
the military are not only apolitical we
are nonpartisan you can't pick sides
June 1st 2020 was that a turning point
for you as chairman I think it was yeah
I realized that
stepped into a political Minefield and I
shouldn't
have he's talking about the day when
President Trump threatened to invoke the
Insurrection act and deploy the US Army
to put down the unrest on America's
streets on the evening of June 1st after
demonstrators near the White House were
removed by
force chairman Millie dressed in battle
fatigues joined president Trump and
members of his cabinet in a march across
lafay Square to St John's Church where
Mr Trump posed for
photographs 10 days later General Millie
apologized in a speech to graduates of
the National Defense University my
presence in that moment and in that
environment created a perception of the
military involved in domestic Politics
as a commissioned uniformed officer it
was a mistake that I have learned from
it's rare for a chairman to apologize
publicly well you know I grew up here in
Boston I'm Irish Catholic and my mother
and father taught me that when you make
a mistake you admit it you got a
confession you say 10 hell Mar is an Al
father everybody makes mistakes and and
the key is how you deal with a mistake
after you apologized former president
Trump said you choked like a
dog yeah I'm not going to comment on
anything the former president has said
or not said General Millie did tell us
he was so disillusioned with the former
president's actions he nearly resigned
instead according to Former Defense
secretary Mark esper he and the general
made a pact to protect the military from
becoming politicized or misused it's
also been reported that you spent
several days several drafts of
resignation letters right I was very
struck by the one that was published in
which you said to the president it is my
deeply held belief that you are ruining
the international order causing
significant damage to our country
overseas that was fought so hard by the
greatest Generation in
1945 that generation has fought against
fascism has fought against Nazism has
fought against extremism it's now
obvious to me that you don't understand
that World Order you don't think Donald
Trump understood what World War II was
fought over I don't know what uh
president former president Trump uh
understood about World War II or or or
or anything else uh I I can tell you
that from 1914 to
1945 150 million people or thereabouts
were slaughtered in the conduct of great
power war and in 1945 the United States
took the initiative and drafted up a set
of rules that govern the world to this
day those rules are under stress
internationally President Putin is a
direct frontal assault on those rules uh
China is trying to revise those rules to
their own benefit but that's one thing
to say that China is threatening that
World Order and Russia is threatening
that world order to say that the
Commander in Chief Donald Trump was
ruining the international order in
causing significant damage what did you
see that caused you to write that I I
would say that it's got to be more than
walking into Lafayette Square and
uniform there was a wide variety of
initiatives that were ongoing one of
them of course was with drawing troops
out of NATO those were initiatives that
placed at risk um you know I think
America's rolling the world now that is
uh the opposite of uh what my parents
and and uh 18 million others wore the
uniform for World War II to defeat
General Millie doesn't just Revere the
greatest Generation he was raised by it
his father was a Navy medic who served
in the Pacific Campaign including at the
Battle of iima his mother joined the
naval Reserve to work as a
nurse well this was and Still Remains a
very patriotic neighborhood after the
war they settled in Winchester a small
town north of Boston almost every
single uh male and female parent that
was here they're all World War Two
Veterans of one kind or another the
whole block really a lot ofbody yeah
100% and interesting no officers uh
these were all 100% enlisted and they
had their own opinions of officers too
including your parents right oh yeah
yeah during high school he was recruited
to play ice hockey at Princeton
University and decided to join The
Reserve officer training Corps or
Roc after graduating in 1980 he went on
to become a paratrooper and serve in
Special Forces he did one com tour in
Iraq and three in Afghanistan raise your
right hand this past may he returned to
Princeton to commission the graduating
Roc class congratulations to every one
of you and took a particular interest
all right Cadets in a few of the young
officers whose language skills are
currently in high demand I speak Chinese
sir Chinese is really really important
to us does anybody else speak Chinese
whoa 1 two 3 4 five if you speak Chinese
if you don't mind I'd like to get your
names uh and we'll see where life takes
you guys we the United States need to
take the challenge the military
challenge of China extraordinarily
seriously how concerned are you that
military to military Communications are
not happening right now with China yeah
I think we need to get that established
uh we had them for a period of time and
they've dropped off so channels of
communication are important in order to
deescalate in time of Crisis general
Millie says he held a total of five
calls with his Chinese military
counterparts during the Trump and Biden
administrations but it was his last two
calls during the final months of the
Trump presidency that got the attention
of the press Congress and the former
president himself why did you think it
was so important to call your Chinese
military counterpart in the aftermath of
the January 6th attacks that's an
example of deescalation so there was
clear indications uh that the Chinese
were very concerned about what they were
observing here in the United States you
see some movement of Chinese military
equipment I w't go over anything
classified um so I won't discuss exactly
what we saw or didn't see or what we
heard or didn't hear I will just say
that uh there was clear indications that
the Chinese are very concerned president
Trump recently said that your dealings
with China were so egregious that in
Times Gone by the punishment would have
been
death that's right he said that but for
the record was there anything
inappropriate or treasonous about the
calls you made to China absolutely not
zero none and not only that they were
authorized and they coordinated uh
Congress knows that we've answered these
questions several different times in
writing were you giving the Chinese
information about thinking of the
president of the United States the
specific conversation was I think in
accordance with the intent of the
Secretary of Defense which was to make
sure the Chinese knew that we were not
going to attack them why did the Chinese
think that the US under then president
Trump was going to attack them the
Chinese were concerned about uh what
what is commonly referred to in in the
English language like an October
surprise Wag the Dog sort of thing uh
they were wrong they were not reading us
right look at the president Trump was
not going to attack China uh and they
needed to know that China Russia and the
war in Ukraine are now the problem of
his successor Air Force General Charles
Q Brown
Jr there are also areas of concern
closer to home last year the Army missed
recruiting numbers by 15,000 Soldiers
the worst shortfall in decades
confidence in the US military is at its
lowest in two decades do you bear any
personal responsibility for that
absolutely I think I think as the leader
of the military the uniform military I
think that I am part of that for sure I
think the walk from the White House to
the St John's Church I think that uh
helped create some of that I think the
withdrawal from Afghanistan uh helped
create some of that but I would also say
the United States military is still one
of the most respected institutions in
the United States by a long shot uh by
huge margin you know I I think we've uh
taken a slip back a little bit and I
think we need to improve on
that General Mark Milly on the future of
warfare does it make war more likely it
could at 60 Minutes overtime.com in the
character of War which is