not since Watergate has an attorney
general been at the center of such a
firestorm Merrick Garland's justice
department is Prosecuting both former
president Trump and the son of President
Biden caught in the middle is this
70-year-old former prosecutor and
well-respected judge with a long history
as a moderate we met Garland Friday in
Washington he told us that he devoted
his life to the rule of law because of
his family's struggle to escape the
Holocaust now he's responsible for
prosecutions that will shape the future
of the nation in a rare interview the
Attorney General told us that in the
Trump and Biden trials ahead his
prosecutors will pursue Justice without
fear and without
favor the story will continue in a
moment
we do not have one rule for republicans
and another rule for Democrats we don't
have one rule for foes and another for
friends we don't have one rule for the
powerful another for the powerless for
the rich or for the poor based on
ethnicity we have only one rule and that
one rule is that we follow the facts and
the law and we reach the decisions
required by the Constitution and we
protect civil liberties are you
essentially saying as attorney general
to the American people trust me well in
the end I I suppose it does in the end
come down to trust but it's not just me
it's Decades of the of the Norms of this
department that are part of the DNA of
the career prosecutors who are running
the investigation um and supervising the
investigations that you're talking about
former president Trump faces two Federal
trials one for allegedly hoarding
classified documents and covering it up
the other for allegedly conspiring to
see power after the 2020 election
attorney general Garland has said little
about this and we wanted to understand
why well I think the first thing to
understand is because these are pending
cases because there are two federal
indictments the long-standing rule in
the Justice Department is that we can't
comment about pending cases where does
that rule come from what's the point one
reason is to protect the privacy and
civil liberties of the person who's
under investigation it's to protect
Witnesses who also may or may not become
public later in an investigation and
then finally it's to protect the
investigation itself um investigations
proceed in many different directions
eventually coming to a fruition a
decision to charge or not charge about a
particular thing or not and if Witnesses
and potential subjects knew everything
that the investigators had previously
looked at and we about to look at it
could well change testimony it could
well make make Witnesses unavailable to
us and this is not peculiar to the Trump
investigations well this is a rule for
all investigations this is part of what
we call our Justice manual it's been
there for probably at least 30 years and
probably longer than that help us
understand the
timing these prosecutions of the former
president are happening during the
campaign you could make the argument
that it's the worst possible
time the justice department has general
practice IES about not making
significant overt steps or charging
within a month or so of an election we
are clearly outside that uh that time
frame uh in these cases um prosecutors
special counsel they follow the facts in
the law where they lead when they've
gotten the amount of evidence necessary
to make a charging decision and have
decided that a charge is warranted
that's when they bring their cases the
investig ation itself has determined the
timing yes exactly right your critics
say that it's time to ruin Mr Trump's
chances in the election well that's
absolutely not true justice department
prosecutors are nonpartisan they don't
allow partisan considerations to play
any role in their determinations the
prosecutor in the Trump cases is Jack
Smith he was named by Garland to be
special counsel that's a job under the
regulations of the justice department
designed to give Smith broad
independence from the department and
from the White House the most important
aspect of the regulations is that the
special councel is not subject to the
day-to-day supervision of anyone in the
Justice Department you are not in
communication with the president or any
member of his administration with regard
to the investigation of former president
Trump no I am not if President Biden
asked you you to take action with regard
to the Trump investigation what would
your reaction be I am sure that that
will not happen um but I would not uh do
anything um in that regard um and if
necessary I would resign but I there is
no sense that anything like that will
happen have you ever had to tell him
hands off these investigations Mr
President no because he has never tried
to put hands on these investigations
separately president President Biden
himself is the subject of a special
councel investigation into whether he
improperly held classified documents
after he was vice president his son
Hunter Biden is the target of a 4year
investigation into his business deals
and his taxes he's been indicted for
lying about drug abuse when he bought a
gun Republicans accus special counsel
David Weiss of slow walking the hunter
Biden investigation the allegation is Mr
attorney
general that what is described in some
quarters as the Biden justice
department is taking it easy on the
president's son well look um this
investigation began under David Weiss uh
David Weiss is a long-standing career
prosecutor and he was appointed by Mr
Trump as the United State's Attorney uh
for the District of Delaware I promised
at my nomination hearing that I would
continue him on in that position uh and
that I would not interfere with this
investigation you are not participating
in those decisions no Mr Weiss is making
those decisions the White House is not
attempting to influence those decisions
absolutely not and he said we won't have
to take his word for it under justice
department regulations a special counsel
must write a final report which I will
make public to the extent um permissible
under the law um that is required to
explain their prosecutive decisions
their decisions to prosecute or not
prosecute and their strategic decisions
along the way usually the special
councils have testified at the end of
their reports and I expect that that
will be the case here how's your
relationship with the president it must
be
Frosty I have a good working
relationship with the president good
perhaps but maybe not close the
president addressed the question in
August when he spotted Garland at a
White House Event attorney general
Garland haven't seen you in a long while
good to see you Secretary of homelet you
think I'm kidding I'm
[Music]
not attorney general Garland leads
115,000 employees prosecutors agents of
the FBI and other federal law
enforcement additional security is now
assigned to protect judges and
prosecutors after the Trump cases Drew
death threats political violence is
among Garland's gravest
concerns people can argue with each
other as much as they want and as
vociferously as they want but the one
thing they may not do is use violence
and threats of violence to alter the
outcome and an important aspect of this
is the American people themselves the
American people must protect each
other they must
ensure that they treat each
other with Civility and kindness listen
to opposing views argue as vifer usly as
they want but refrain from violence and
threats of violence that's the only way
this democracy Will Survive why do you
feel so strongly about
that well I feel it for a number of
reasons and number of things that I've
seen but for my own family who who uh
fled uh religious persecution in Europe
um and some members who did not
uh survive when they got to the United
States the United States
protect it guaranteed uh that they could
practice their religion they could vote
they could do all the things they
thought a democracy would provide um
that's the difference between this
country and many other countries and
it's my responsibility it's the Justice
Department's responsibility to ensure
that that difference continues that we
protect each
other two of your ancestors were
murdered in the
Holocaust yes is that why you devoted
yourself to the
law yes uh that's I would say that's why
I devoted myself to the rule of law uh
to Public Service uh to try and to
ensure that the rule of law um um
governs this country and continues to
govern this country Merrick Garland has
spent a life in the law m e r r i c k g
a r l a n d he's the associate Deputy
attorney general at Justice he oversaw
the Oklahoma City bombing case at Act of
political terrorism later after nearly
two decades as a federal appeals court
judge he was nominated to the US Supreme
Court by President Obama but Republicans
stalled the nomination for 10 months
until Donald Trump was sworn in
president-elect Biden picked Garland for
Attorney
General on the same day the capital was
attacked that became one of the largest
investigations in the Department's
history we've U arrested and brought
charges against more than 1,00 uh people
um there are uh more to come um the
videos that uh every single person uh
happen to have on their phones uh that
security cameras had that bystanders had
that the media had at the time uh
disclosed faces some of which we have
not yet been able to connect uh to
people you're looking for new suspects
new defendants still yeah there it's not
that they're new suspects but there they
are people that we haven't found yet why
do these prosecutions mean so much to
you because this is a fundamental aspect
of our democracy if we can't ensure that
this kind of behavior doesn't recur it
will occur the prosecutions we bring are
deterrence against that from happening
Garland knows he will be vilified no
matter how the Trump and Biden cases are
decided his job he told us was to take
the arrows for the Department he has
learned to embrace the pain that comes
with the job the youngest right now is
Riot Mitchell Forever 8 months old and
we saw that at DEA headquarters where he
was surrounded by those lost to the
opioid epidemic is the attorney general
and their grieving families meeting them
he told us reminds him of why he fights
and whom he is fighting for thank you
for being here and listening to us I
represent the American people um I don't
represent the president I represent the
American people and likewise I am not
congress's prosecutor I work for the
American
people and if democracy is an emotional
subject for Merrick Garland maybe it's
because he has witnessed how suddenly it
can be threatened in Oklahoma City and
Washington
DC when the history of this
extraordinary time is written what is
the best that Merrick Garland can hope
for look I think it's the best any
public servant can hope for that we've
done our best that we pass on a justice
department that uh continues to pursue
the rule of law and protect it uh and
it's it's the same thing that every
generation has to Hope um that we can
pass our democracy on in working order
um to the next uh generation that picks
up the torch and is responsible when
we're finished uh to continue that
job