conventionally 60 Minutes doesn't
profile the same subject twice in two
seasons but convention doesn't intersect
with Pro Football Hall of Famer Dion
Sanders last fall we met Sanders in
Mississippi where he was coaching
Jackson State to prominence in a
conference of historically black
colleges and universities then the man
who calls himself coach prime high
stepped it to Boulder to the University
of Colorado taking his blazingly
singular Style with him there he hasn't
just awoken a dormant program but has
transformed it into the talk of college
football if not American Sports Sanders
is revered he is reviled but a Sudden
Impact is indisputable for the second
time in two radically different
environments Unapologetic as ever he's
shaken the sport like a snow globe
the story will continue in a moment
are you the change agent are you the
ultimate change agent I make a
difference I truly make a difference I
make folks nervous man I give folks
moving in their seat I get folks
twirling their thumbs I get them
thinking and second guessing they said
you know have you ever been so clean
that you walked in and somebody looked
down at you then they looked at
themselves they had to check themselves
because you were so clean I have that
effect that's the vibe you're getting I
have that effect
that was some good game right there but
God that was good we ain't got next
we got now
[Music]
[Applause]
this was the scene in the locker room
two weekends ago
[Applause]
before the Colorado Buffaloes and their
new coach Dion Sanders opened the season
to 21 Point Underdog at PCU good job
Colorado was fresh off a 1 in 11 season
TCU was fresh from playing in last
season's national championship game
with skill and will the Buffaloes won
45-42 behind their Star Quarterback
shudor Sanders but the real Focus as
ever was on shidur's 56 year old father
it was his first win as coach of a power
five School the highest level of college
football do you feel like you were
underestimated if you come here and it's
I don't know if coach Prime can win you
must have heard what some of these other
coaches were saying both secretly
fear yeah that's fear that's like hey
man
shoot we don't want to let that Engine
That Could get going because if that
Engine That Could get going he gonna
start saying I think I can I think I can
the sooner the lady he gonna start
saying I know I can I know I can't then
soon the lady going to start saying I
did that
his Colorado debut Drew national
attention and monster TV ratings
interest compounded last weekend when
the Buffaloes played before the biggest
home crowd in 15 years in beat rival
Nebraska
this weekend both Fox and ESPN
dispatched their pregame shows the rock
included to Boulder then the Buffaloes
rallied late to beat Colorado State in a
double overtime Thriller
three games into the season the
foothills of the Rockies marked the
unlikely epicenter of an entire sport
what's this been like for you
um it's it's been a lot of fun
Rick George who hired coach Prime has
been Colorado's athletic director for a
decade it's great for us to be able to
bring this program back to relevancy and
we had failed in my previous nine years
10 years fair to call this bit of a Hail
Mary it wasn't a Hail Mary but it was a
moment in time for our University and
our athletic department that we were
either going to be relevant or we were
going to be irrelevant
it's too early to quantify the full
Prime effect but merchandise sales up
819 from last season Instagram followers
up more than tenfold season tickets sold
out
Sanders might be the ideal coach for
these shifting times in college football
another son Dion JR is part of the army
of videographers filming the team
non-stop for YouTube and an upcoming
docu-series
steam won one game last season is that
in a way a point of appeal God wouldn't
relocate me to something that was
successful that don't make sense to it
he had to find the most
disappointing in the most uh difficult
task
in this
is what it was and this is what it is
and I love that
this wasn't dissimilar to what he told
us last year that God had called him
collect to come to Jackson State
University and Elevate yes the football
program but also all hbcus
he stayed three seasons but the same
night last December that JSU won the
conference Championship Sanders
announced he was off to Colorado to
climb Another Mountain you left Jackson
State and you left quickness
leave quick I left what I was supposed
to leave
to leave most coaches get a new job and
they leave expeditiously I finished the
task you say finish the task was there
was there more work you could have done
in Jackson or I think we did a
tremendous job in Jackson I think we
laid down the tremendous blueprint
we tried to press Sanders on the
circumstances surrounding his abandoning
the mission at Jackson State he's hinted
the school's lack of Forward Thinking
may have factored in his decision but on
this topic he was about as elusive as he
was returning punts for touchdowns in
the NFL what'd you tell his kids when
you left
um opportunity
called sooner and later in life there
will be opportunity that knocks at your
door and at this juncture in my life I
felt like the opportunity for not only
me but for my kids as well was
tremendous not only did we take several
kids from that team
three trainers
maybe 12 to 14 staffers so we afforded
to give people a tremendous opportunity
here
the distance between Jackson and Boulder
is a thousand miles and immeasurably
further culturally Sanders went from a
city that is 83 percent black to one
that is one percent black from a place
with a Water Crisis to the kind of
hipster college town where there's a
shop devoted to kites what are your
first impressions uh beautiful
unbelievable just the whole peace and
serenity of it all I never fathom coming
here I ain't never even vacation here
man I ain't never been skiing or
whatever you call it snowboarding or
whatever all the stuff you know ain't
never done none of that you don't even
fly fish no I don't I fish
I'm fly why I fish but I don't fly fish
still he wasted no time ingratiating
himself in the community including a
visit to Peggy coppam a 98 year old
Buffalo Super Fan
how about good looking this
he was less embracing of the incumbent
Colorado players at the first team
meeting in December Sanders encouraged
players to enter the transfer portal an
open market for athletes to find new
schools I promise you it's my job to get
rid of them and make room for Superior
Talent he planned to bring in more than
50 players eventually transferred out
you got here and you didn't pull punches
you told some of these guys have I ever
you take a team that's won one game and
you fired a whole coaching staff so who
did the coaching staff recruit
the kids
so the kids are just
as much to blame as the coaching staff
and I came to the conclusion that a
multitude of them can help us get to
where we wanted to go you told most of
these guys the more you jump in the more
room you're going to make those of you
we don't run off we're going to try to
make you quit yeah you made it very
clear yeah now if you went for that if
you were able to let words run you off
you ain't for us because we're old
school staff we coach hard we coach tuck
we're disciplined narrants so if you're
allowing verbiage to run you off because
you don't feel secure with your ability
you ain't for us
if some kid said you know what no I'm
staying you're not going to run me off
with your words right stay so prove it
I'm sure that your straight talk was
appreciated by some but is this scorched
Earth policy good for for college
football or for the kids I think truth
is good for kids we're so busy lying we
don't even recognize the truth no more
in society we want everybody to feel
good that's not that's not the way life
is now it is my job to make sure I have
what we need to win
that makes a lot of people feel good
winning does I got to push back on this
you're a father of college athletes yes
if they called you and say hey we got a
new coach and they're telling me to get
in the transfer portal I say son you
must be you must not be doing well
that's what you said you must not be
doing well because you should be an
asset and not a liability I'm honest
with my kids his kids include shador the
star quarterback in Shiloh of starting
safety if you guys have any idea that
you are going to be this good and
capture the country the way you have
yeah you did yeah we both didn't come
here
have our dad closing just to lose
a year ago to the day we watched the
door fleeing and Zing touchdown passes
at Jackson State
but there were questions about whether
he could do the same against stiffer
competition well in his first two games
at Colorado he threw for nearly 1 000
yards without an interception
you were putting up big numbers at
Jackson State you're doing it here
against teams and the Big Ten yeah the
big 12. must be gratifying yeah now
these two games was the most yards I
passed for in my career
so it's just it's just exciting knowing
that you know to translate and like on a
bigger stage I just feel better he's
also and again welcome to today's
college sports translated his success
into riches thanks to nil name image
likeness income so much so he drives a
one hundred and ninety thousand dollar
Mercedes Maybach and chidur might not
even be the team's best player Travis
Hunter also followed coach Prime from
Jackson to Colorado his coach lets him
play offense and defense virtually
unheard of in the modern college game
you've got two really good Heisman
quality players on this team yes your
son and Travis Hunter yes sir first half
of the first game of the season you're
already publicly talking about Travis
Hunter's Heisman chances who does that a
a coach that loves his kids the coach
that understands that's what those kids
desire and I supposed to do that that's
what we told them when they were coming
and choosing to play for us my kids that
play for me they didn't choose a
university
they chose me that's the difference
coaches have chosen to join Sanders as
well the staff he overhauled and
upgraded includes former head coaches
and former coordinators from schools
like Alabama now that you're a power
Five Guy mm-hmm who's the best coach in
college football today
let me see let me see a mirror so I can
look at it
you feel that
you think I'm gonna sit up here and tell
you somebody else
you think you think that's the way I
operate that somebody else got that on
me but I tell you this
I love and I adore and I respect and
every time I do a commercial with Coach
Saban it's a gift just sitting in his
presence and hearing him and and
throwing something else out there so I
could hear his viewpoint on it because
he's forgotten more things than I may
ever accomplish so I'm a student looking
up to this wonderful teacher saying
just just throw me a crumb of what you
know
for all the bling and Bluster there is
some humility and the current Mania may
die down a bit as Colorado faces a
Welter of tougher opponents the rest of
the season
but Dion Sanders has invigorated the
campus a program an entire sport game
ball Peggy
and damn if
fun give me my theme music
[Applause]