tonight Scott Pelley reports from
Ukraine where he sat down with president
velodimir zielinski in the capital keep
the story will continue in a moment
we met president zielinski as he
prepared to depart key for the United
States this week he will speak at the
U.N and meet President Biden it is a
critical time U.S officials tell us that
over nearly 600 days almost half a
million troops have been killed or
wounded both sides altogether
part of the cost so far of Vladimir
Putin's unprovoked invasion we spoke to
zielinski on Thursday he told us that
his people are dying every day to
prevent World War III
um
we're defending the values of the whole
world zielinski said and these are
Ukrainian people who are paying the
highest price
we are truly fighting for our freedom we
are dying
we're not fiction we're not a book we're
fighting for real with a nuclear state
that threatens to destroy the world
the United States has contributed about
70 billion dollars to your war effort
and I wonder if you expect that level of
support to continue
the United States of America is
supporting Ukraine financially and I'm
grateful for this
I just think they're not supporting only
Ukraine alone if Ukraine Falls Putin
will surely go further what will the
United States of America do when Putin
reaches the Baltic states when he
reaches the Polish border he will
this is a lot of money we have a lot of
gratitude what else must Ukraine do for
everyone to measure our huge gratitude
we are dying in this war
look if Ukraine Falls what will happen
in 10 years just think about it if the
Russians reach Poland what's next a
third world war
what will it take another 70 billion
yeah
I don't have an answer the whole world
has to decide whether we want to stop
Putin or whether we want to start the
beginning of a World War
we can't change Putin Russian Society
has lost the respect of the world they
elected him and re-elected him and
raised a second Hitler they did this we
cannot go back in time but we can stop
it here
Ukraine stopped the Russian advance but
at a terrible cost ruined cities
millions of refugees Untold thousands of
dead
all four Vladimir Putin's nation
building vanity
today the war is fought on a 700 mile
front the red area is the 20 percent of
Ukraine still occupied by Russia this is
where Western donated tanks were
supposed to punch through cutting the
Russian Force in half
but trenches minefields and artillery
stopped the armored Advance now it's an
artillery duel with each side firing
about 40 000 shells a day
Ukrainian infantry is advancing bloody
yards at a time
it's World War One
with drones
how would you describe the fighting at
the front
um
it's a difficult question I'll be
completely honest with you we have the
initiative this is a plus
the Russian offensive and we moved into
a counter-offensive but despite that
it's not very fast it is important that
we are moving forward every day and
liberating territory you have about six
weeks of good weather left and I wonder
after that point will the front be
frozen in place
we need to liberate our territory as
much as possible and move forward even
if it's less than half a mile or a
hundred yards we must do it we can't
lose time forget about the weather and
the like in places that we can't get
through in an armored vehicle let's fly
if we can't fly let's send drones
we mustn't give Putin a break
if the front is stationary Ukrainian
drones have vaulted into Russia itself
hitting the Kremlin warplanes and Moscow
high-rises officially Ukraine does not
acknowledge these attacks the drone
strikes in Russia are being done on your
orders
no not on your order well you know how
is this happening at the shore you know
we don't shoot at the territory of the
Russian Federation
we decided to try the question another
way what message is being sent with
these drone strikes in Russia
you do know that we use our partners
weapons on the territory of Ukraine only
and this is true but these are not
punitive operations such as they carry
out killing civilians but Russia needs
to know that wherever it is whichever
place they use for launching missiles to
strike Ukraine Ukraine has every moral
right to send a response to those places
we are responding to them saying your
sky is not as well protected as you
think
[Music]
last winter it was Ukrainian Skies that
were filled with missiles in a Russian
bombardment to destroy power plants
Millions shivered in the dark
with winter approaching again zielinski
had this warning
they must know if you cut off our power
deprive us of electricity deprive us of
water the privacy of gasoline you need
to know
we have the right to do it to you
Russia takes Solinski seriously now
because Putin's Mass invasion was a
fiasco the red marks where Ukraine
stopped Russia's Advance last year
it also marks the stain of Russia's war
crimes Mr President in traveling around
Ukraine for the last year and a half
we spoke to people in bombed out schools
in chernoheve
we've seen destroyed apartment blocks in
borodianca a bombed Hospital in isium
civilians in a mass grave in bucha these
are not military targets
what is Vladimir Putin trying to do
to break us
and by choosing civilian targets Putin
wanted to achieve exactly this to break
us this person who has made his way with
such bloody actions with everything he
has said cannot be trusted there is no
trust in such a person because he has
not been a human being for a long time
the Russians have suffered Grievous
losses
without resorting to nuclear weapons
and I wonder if you believe that the
threat of nuclear war is now behind us
I think he's going to continue
threatening
he's waiting for the United States to
become less stable he thinks that's
going to happen during the U.S election
he'll be looking for instability in
Europe and the United States of America
he will use the risk of using nuclear
weapons to fuel that instability he will
keep on threatening
that U.S election he mentioned worries
him his negotiations with President
Biden have been contentious at times but
zielinski tends to get what he asks for
even if in zelinski's opinion it's
generally six months too late
this week zelinski will press Mr Biden
for missiles with longer range Congress
is debating another 24 billion dollar
package
and if Ukraine had enough of these
modern systems we would have already
restored the territorial Integrity of
Ukraine we would have already done that
these systems exist are you safe here
we first met zielinski not long after
the invasion when his office was a
blacked out bunker be careful now a year
and a half later we noticed a difference
as we were setting up the interview the
former actor used his talent to mask the
strain he smiled at a compliment to his
wife yeah so great and then instantly he
seemed pulled beneath a depth no one can
know
we don't know what he was thinking it
looked like empathy
for the Lost
and for those who might be saved
[Applause]
our time was solinsky began in silence a
remembrance of the fallen during a
ceremony to award Medals of Valor
[Applause]
Ukrainian officials tell us Ukraine and
Russia have lost their professional
armies now the forces are made up of
volunteers draftees and in Russia's case
prison inmates
zielinski counts his dad in casualty
reports each morning you are the
president but it must be humbling to
meet those men I wonder what they mean
to you
yeah first of all it's a great honor for
me I look into their eyes and it makes
me proud that we have such strong people
because this is a big risk a big risk
you can definitely lose your life for
the sake of saving other lives and when
I say other lives I don't speak in
general I mean my own life the lives of
my children and I understand completely
what risks are involved
that empathy for life has velodimir
zielinski reaching out again to the
United Nations and the United States
hoping to convince the Allies that the
world can be safe only when Ukraine is
whole can you give up
any part of Ukraine for peace
no this is our territory you must have
it all including Crimea
of women
today you and I you said it to me you
saw me awarding people medals well today
is a day like that a week ago I gave
Awards to parents of soldiers who have
been killed there were 24 families of
the Dead there was a woman she was with
three children there were parents very
old they could barely walk and they had
had only one son
one of the women was pregnant she
arrived holding a baby in her arms and
she was pregnant and that baby will
never see
what should I tell them that all of them
died so that we could say it's okay
Russia you can take it all right
it's a difficult job you understand me
right giving awards to people whose
faces show their whole world has
collapsed and all I can give them all I
can give them
is Victory
hello Mr President hear more from Scott
pelly's news making conversation with
President Volo damir zielinski at 60
minutes overtime.com
something don't