60 Minutes rewind
say Denzel and most people would know
you're talking about one of the highest
paid and most popular actors in
Hollywood
but 30 years ago Denzel Washington was
just another unknown struggling New York
actor today he's playing the lead in a
Broadway play and making standard union
wages a fraction of what he'd make in
Hollywood so we went to see it man I
remembered a story he told me five years
ago about an incredible prediction that
he says started it all
I was in my mother's beauty shop
and I was looking in the mirror and I
saw a woman sitting across the room for
me
and she said to my mother bring me a
piece of paper
she said I have a prophecy it's the
God's honest truth I got the piece of
paper and I'll keep it with me all the
time
and she wrote down she said this boy is
going to speak to millions of people
I don't talk about that a lot but I've
kind of felt like well maybe I have some
job to do remember the woman I tell you
about the prophecy that was 30 years
that will be 30 years ago next week
right and then I started acting that
fall so it's kind of interesting coming
back now 30 years later about 20 blocks
from where I started wins
countrymen
and love us Denzel Washington's career
began on the Obscure stage at New York's
Fordham University but today he is
headlining on Broadway appearing in a
modern day production of Shakespeare's
Julius Caesar he plays Brutus one of the
leaders of a plot to kill Caesar not
that I
but that I love Rome more why did you
decide to do this play now I thought it
was a great opportunity to get back on
the stage to get back to my roots and I
get so few opportunities to get on the
stage
so when I do I really like tackling
Shakespeare which is the toughest and
the most rewarding
I mean it took me 30 years but I'm I
finally am doing what I wanted to do
when I started the actors I I started
with in college and we were all snobs
and we thought we would you know make
600 a week in on Broadway or whatever it
was back then we didn't think about
going to Hollywood that was some
Hollywood you didn't do that
but he did and it is his acting in those
Hollywood movies that has made Denzel
Washington a household name happy
birthday you just made my mother's
birthday all right he's been in more
than 30 feature films and won two
Academy Awards best supporting actor for
his portrayal of a runaway slave in the
film Glory Days of training day
officeroy and in 2002 best actor for his
performance as the dirty cop Alonso
Harris in Training Day but I ain't
holding no hands you understand I ain't
babysitting you got today and today only
to show me who and What You're Made Of
You don't like knock his name has become
synonymous with Hollywood box office
Blockbusters most recently he played
Major Ben Marco in a remake of The
Manchurian candidates
big Steel
toe cable Cutters in a chainsaw and they
went to town you've been working a lot
since we talked five years ago you've
done what
seven films since then and since what
year was that 99 yeah okay
I mean it's a lot of work
uh is it
I mean work is like
you know garbage man is work I'm acting
is not work acting is is a privilege and
it's a craft and and all of those things
but uh
it's not work I read that you get 20
million to film now
I heard you make that kind of money too
I'm not there yet are you not there yet
are you finished I thought I was just
getting started tell you something
something may have slipped your mind
but you are addressing a superior
officer you understand me in 2002 in the
film Antoine Fisher Denzel played a Navy
psychiatrist counseling a troubled
sailor cut cut okay in addition tackling
a new role as the film's Director
his face right in our face for our first
shot you know did you enjoy directly
absolutely I'm going to do it again and
when it comes to one or the other I mean
you'd like to do both or do you prefer
acting over directing
um
I look at Clint Eastwood as the model
that's that's I like the way he's doing
things and that's how I'd like to do it
just
segue right on into into more and more
filmmaking a Hollywood director's chair
is a long way from where he grew up in
Mount Vernon A working class suburb
outside New York City
his mother lennis managed that beauty
shop his father Denzel senior was a
Pentecostal preacher who held down two
other jobs Denzel went to church every
Sunday but dreamed of becoming a
professional athlete he spent all of his
free time here at what was then the boys
club
this was an important place for you yep
I lived here my mother would have to
come get me so that you had a time when
you had to come home nine o'clock man I
had a I had a time I knew how to get to
the fish market by 8 54 and by the
chicken joint by 856 in order to make it
home by nine o'clock does she ever have
to come looking for you she did
she would
we were in the park and she came and
they were like I did your mom's here and
I got in the car
and she was screaming so I kind of look
at everybody at the window like like you
know I got this as I was as I was
turning around
so I put my head under the dashboard
just drive mom just drive Denzel says
his mother lennis saved his life when
she scraped together enough money to
send him to Oakland Academy a small
boarding school for boys in Upstate New
York he hadn't been back there for 20
years and was surprised to see his old
school being converted into Condominiums
man it looks so little now
my God Denzel was 14 when he came here
one of only a handful of
African-American students how did you
end up here
I am
was in public school Mount Vernon High
School
and my mother decided it was best
to get me out of there
before
I ended up
where a lot of my friends are now
in you know in the grave
in the penitentiary how were you up here
I mean were were you a bad kid
no
angrier as time went along what were you
angry about come on let's take a walk in
here
right about here
was a chair
and I was sitting in the mess hall
whatever we called it and they told me
your mother's here
what did I do I did something wrong
and I came right about here sat down and
uh she said your father and I aren't
together anymore
you're going to be with me you know I
don't know what I'm going to do but
we're going to work it out so this is
where I found out my parents were
getting divorced right here right right
here right here I remember it like it
was yesterday
so to answer your question about anger I
think I started getting a little trouble
after that started getting in fights
and almost kicked out of school but his
mother talked the Headmaster into giving
him another chance you owe her a lot I
ordered everything
I assume you told her that in many ways
the story will continue after this
really intimate House Denzel made the
most of that second chance building a
career that has brought him riches Fame
and critical Acclaim and so why would an
actor who makes millions for one movie
risk his reputation by taking a role
that pays Seventeen hundred dollars a
week what do you get out of it I mean
when when you go through this
performance eight times a week
it's like retooling the the lights come
up with the curtain goes up and it's an
actor's medium on stage and and you know
it's it's flying by the seat of your
pants you got to keep going it's live
things happen we're still going through
things things fall and lights don't work
you forget lines or whatever happens and
that's good that's good exercise cell
phones go off cell phones go off one of
these days I'm going to respond to it in
iambic pentameter answer at that
my Lord my Lord it is for you
Heavens I'd rather coin my heart this
production has traded ancient Rome's
togas and tunics for suits ties and
camouflage
it is set in Modern Times And is
intended to be evocative of power
struggles in cities like Washington or
Baghdad what makes the play Julius
Caesar relevant today
well again I mean it's it's what ifs we
do have
leaders in the world that think they're
Gods I mean and it's not just
governments it's corporations it's you
know unfortunately not a lot has changed
I think it's a part of the human
condition
are open two weeks ago to mixed reviews
but Denzel says reviews don't affect him
because he doesn't read them anyway the
show is nearly sold out for his
scheduled 112 performances that will run
until June performances that give him
something he doesn't get in Hollywood
how do you feel at the end
of a performance
I mean this is not an easy role thankful
you know I run off stage I wipe the
makeup off I say a quick prayer I hear
the people out there clap and you get a
sense saying oh is it two bows tonight
is it one is it three you know and uh
but a relief
you know
Joy
it it you don't get that in the movies
making movies you all the feelings I'm
getting night after night I mean people
are like man you got a hundred to go but
I'm like yeah I'm enjoying every one of
them