you'd expect a 600-year old sport to
have played through its identity crisis
not the case for pool the Sport's very
name comes from pooling money to
determine odds and wagering lens pool
Mystique hustling and pool go together
like atick and chalk but that's as much
a curse as a blessing how can a sport
Thrive at the highest level when so much
of it exists in the shadows well here
comes van boning from Rapid City as we
first told you in December at age 39
with no interest in gambling van boning
is arguably the best American player
ever to break a rack and was ranked
number one in the world for 2022 he also
happens to be deaf can the South Dakota
kid help turn pool popular in bars and
basement but not on TV into a proper Pro
Sport we hit the circuit with him to
find
out the story we'll continue in a
moment another day another casino hotel
Shane Van boning spends 300 days a year
on the road playing professional pool
today he's clocking in early at the
Jamboree of American pool tournaments
the Derby City
Classic held every January outside
Louisville Derby City is a colorful
expression of pool's split personality
downstairs a felt ocean drawing dozens
of the world's best practitioners they
compete 12 hours a day for 9 days in
multiple
events this winner is smiling ear to ear
and his check tops out at
$166,000 but upstairs it's a different
economy behold pool's zestier side popup
action rooms standing room only where
Pros amateurs and wannabes alike come to
the table for unofficial competition the
signs say no smoking and no gambling and
we sure didn't see any smoking tens
sometimes hundreds of thousands of
dollars Big Timber they call it change
hands until the sun comes up one player
we didn't see gambling upstairs Shane
Van bony a generational Talent known for
his killer
break van boning has won the US Open
five times and been named player of the
decade deaf since birth he wears hearing
aids and shuts down any question this
makes it harder for him to play
pool it's actually a big Advantage for
me how's that you know when I play po
tournament I can just shut it off do you
shut your hearing aids off when you play
when I want my first Uso and I had
everything off I was focused total
silence yes I'm totally like 100% zon in
never more zoned in than in 2018 when he
led the United States to victory over
Europe at the muscone cup P's answer to
golf's Rider cup and he is going for it
he closed it out with an off angle long
distance 1 n combo this highrisk High
reward pressure packed shot what a shot
Shane Van boning and Team
USA unbelievable finish think you could
have made that
shot we went to Rapid City South Dakota
a side pocket of America to Van Bon's
pool hall where he explained that making
balls disappear into pockets is only
half of pool Excellence it's also about
setting up your neck shot
Q ball control they call it and I'm
going to make the Q ball stop right here
so I can shoot the two in the
side then I'm
going you did that how how did you do
that just hit it right below Center so
now it lines up that next ball perfectly
yeah I'm so struck by the geometry of
all this yeah I love geometry it's all
about the angles van boning says he can
see every angle on the table a six sense
that comes from practicing as much as 10
hours a day shooting half a million
balls a year I want to make the shot
perfect the only way to hit it perfect
you got to do it over and over and over
can you be perfect in this
sport
no I tried so hard so all these years
van boning comes by it honestly his
grandfather Gary Bloomberg a known
trickshot artist opened pool halls off
I90 easy access for Hustlers passing
across the Great Plains but these rooms
were familyfriendly places so much so
Shane got his first pool queue when he
was two and went to the pool room every
day after school not just to play but to
escape kids who picked on him for being
deaf how bad did it get the kid would
start throwing Ros at me they would put
gum in my hair and then I would go home
to my mom I'd be going home crying you
know and then she made me feel feel
better by asking me you want to go to
the pool room why did coming to the pool
room make you feel better you know when
you walk in the pool room what do you
see you know you see people having a
good time but it was more than that he
had prodigious ability for thinking
multiple Strokes ahead when van boning
was 18 he hit the road he and his uncle
loaded into an RV looking for money
games came to play pool fats of course
they did the Hustler that stealth
roadman armed only with a wooden stick
in confidence divorcing the locals from
their cash has been romanticized for
decades not least by Paul Newman this
reporter was so taken by po hustling he
once wrote a book about it for Van
boning the romance hit the Rocks
abruptly yeah I actually was playing the
pool in Tennessee and I was playing this
guy for money and we were playing for a
whole lot and he was
losing and he picked up the key ball and
threw it at me where'd he hit you he hit
me right on the chest it's the kind of
thing you do to start a fight yeah how'd
you react I told my Uncle I said I don't
want to do this anymore I don't want to
live on the road anymore it's just too
dangerous here we go for the title he
chose to go legit and began playing and
winning proper tournaments though less
lucrative than the rambling gambling
life van boning enjoyed being a
professional did you worry that coming
in off the road was going to impact your
your finances
I know some of the pool players like the
top pool players were making money so if
they can do it I can do it but pool is a
deceptively tricky sport next up two
superpowers Collide just ask Shane's
Scottish counterpart Jason Shaw another
top player earlier this year Shaw holed
up in a Virginia pool room for 5 days
and broke the straight pool record
making 74 shots in a row the stuff that
happens in pool will completely screw
your brain up what do you mean you'll
see shots that and you'll be like how
did that happen you'll you'll hear that
all day how did that land over there did
you see that how that went in in pool
you see at every game something weird
will happen does that make it more
exhilarating or more frustrating both
mentally you want to like flip the table
at some point you ever flipped a table
no I've thought about it a few times
people come in how hard could it be it's
just a rectangle with six and then 20
minutes later there's still 15 balls on
the table they've not poted a ball and
the guy's like scratching his head like
thought this was easy it's
not we watched you at Derby City play
Jason Shaw Jason who yeah is he rival
yeah it's been going on for several
years now he's a great player and um
we're always going to have a battle you
okay with that yeah you have to accept
losing if you don't accept losing you're
just you're going to go crazy I'll stick
is the ice right here if having a rival
is Central to being being an elite
athlete so is this leaving time to clear
your head so it was we found ourselves
following Shane Van boning out on to
Paola Lake in the Black
Hills van boning goes fishing season be
damned every morning when he's back home
we didn't catch any fish we did catch
van bony's drift though his take on the
virtues of complete
silence vanity plate notwithstanding few
extravagances come with being number one
in pool the ragtag pro tour barely
televised in the US struggles to draw
much interest or investment outside of
pool die hards how many sponsors do you
have I have six sponsors cues and tables
and Pool Products yes and any sponsors
outside of pool no what can a top player
make top and pool can make only six
figures half expenses maybe five figures
no one's making a million bucks as a
pool player it never
happened van boning says cleaning up the
sport doing away with back room money
games would lure big corporate sponsors
big media deals and grow professional
pool we saw firsthand his discomfort
with gambling and all that comes with it
when we interviewed you in in dery city
I don't if you remember the the
interview was interrupted you you recall
what
happened oh the
gambling was that what happened yeah
it was morning at Derby City and the
action upstairs from the night before
was still
simmering they
arguing over the course of a few minutes
two players who' bet on a game nearly
came to blows you cannot gamble you know
van boning could only shake his head it
got to be a clean sport Ender prop
pool's unlikely new Guardian Emily
Fraser of the British sports promoter
matchroom the company recently revamp
Pro darts and snooker in the UK
streamlining their circuits and turning
top players into celebrities who make
millions oh that's where the tra sits
Fraser is tasked with doing the same for
pool and she says gambling is the least
of her worries what's the state of
professional pool today ah an absolute
mess why' you say that the first ever US
Open that I did in
2019 oh my gosh the players turned up
they were in jeans when I'm going hang
on a second like what's happening here
why is this guy turning up in jeans
Fraser has asked Pro players to dress
the part but she won't ask them to give
up their side hustles now all of the
basement tables and the money matches I
think that's brilliant and that can
still yeah I think that it's fantastic
because it's got the history behind it
you're okay if people are still they're
gambling and playing money games as far
as I'm concerned in a couple years time
they won't need to have any money it'll
be obsolete the market will do its thing
exactly but right now now it's not
viewed as this professional sport and it
has all the ingredients to be one she
standardize the format this is
commercialized sponsor friendly nineball
not the solids and Stripes eight ball
you've likely played in October at the
US Open held in Atlantic City Fraser
brought in bigger live audiences and
ramped up TV production she's kept one
pool Hallmark the Smoke Filled Room
close but no cigar there's a machine
puffing away in the corner When the
Smoke cleared there was Shane Van
boning he was fresh off winning his
first world championship sealing his
status at top the sport he confided to
us that he'd slept with the trophy for a
month van boning is mobbed at pool
tournaments but can still walk through
an airport unbothered well he's no
LeBron James and I totally understand
that and I recognize that um it's our
job to turn that around it is our
responsibility to turn that world number
one prize money from
$80,000 to a million so it's prize money
it's more events and let's get these
players known you've got to fall in love
with them are they lovable yes some of
them the health of the sport also
depends on minting a new generation of
elite players so this tournament had a
junior division held alongside the pros
and named what else the Shane Van boning
Jr open these are future Pros oh yeah
definitely definitely they have so much
passion for the game and then I'm going
to shoot the Shish back at the pool hall
in Rapid City we experience pool's highs
and lows in the same
hour didn't even let me hit a ball ever
the sports gentleman Shane Van boning
wouldn't let us leave without setting us
up to s a trick shot pool may or may not
clean up its act but any sport that can
provide this kind of pure simple thrill
just go right down the middle yep right
down the middle you reckon it'll survive
just
[Laughter]
fine you got
that